yt5s.com-Cardano360 March 2022:
Welcome to your March edition of
Cardano, 360, your monthly catch-up
with the people and projects
building out the Cardona ecosystem.
Now, before we begin, make sure you
like subscribe and hit that bell icon
for all the latest Cardona content
and news from the team here at.
Later in the show, we'll be checking
in with Kevin, John, and Nigel for a
preview of the June vessel hard fork.
We'll also meet a new member of
the team, head of ecosystem growth,
Morgan Scofield, to find out more
about a central car Dano, a new
site, covering all things, cut on it.
And if you're into dogs and NFTs, you
might want to stick around till the
end for a bit of a special message.
Well with that slightly cryptic note,
let's start with something a little
more tangible yield and liquidity.
Now, earlier this week, Wei financial
announced a new fund, and I had an
opportunity to catch up with IOG his
nickname back to learn more about
this new program wave CEO, David
Sima, and Ken Kadama from Emergo
will also drop by to say a few words.
So Nick welcome.
Now, as I understand it, this fund is
ultimately about driving liquidity and
supporting growth for defy on Cardona.
Yes.
The objective of the fund is to
help jumpstart the defined ecosystem
by providing liquidity for a
lot of dApps, specifically Dexis
and lenders to help bring total
value locked or TVL on chain to.
Perhaps you can explain what we mean
by liquidity and why projects need it
in early stages and defy ecosystems.
It's important to enable a good user
experience for things like swaps.
So when there's adequate liquidity in a
Dex or within a decentralized exchange,
you need that to facilitate trading
activity and to have trade executions
happen in a timely manner for users.
Liquidity is a pretty
fundamental concept and.
There needs to be an adequate amount
of a given resource or a currency or
a token in this particular case or
pairs of tokens more specifically.
So in defy, there's often pairs of
tokens that are set up with each other
in a pool so that when trades occur,
they can happen in a timely fashion and
they can literally help the liquidity
providers gain a return on those assets.
As a liquidity provider, I put
in a certain amount of an asset
or a token, and I generally see
rewards or return for doing so.
And as a user who executes a swap these,
these balanced pools of assets are used
to literally execute the mechanics of
those swaps behind the scenes and, you
know, make trades go through and within
a certain number of milliseconds often.
And if you don't have enough, Then
those traits can occur in that time.
We fashioned and essentially, you know,
a lot of these exchanges will struggle to
perform within a certain amount of time.
So now we talk a lot about collaboration
and partnership and these being
key to growth of the ecosystem.
We'll hear from Ken, from Emergo,
and also from David Siemer wave in a
moment, but from an IOT perspective,
what's the ultimate goal here from an
IOT perspective, our goal is always to
support our community and developers
are number one in our committee.
And demonstrate that they're number one.
We are backing investment
managers like wave.
And so our, our partners in terms of
Emergo and this way we can not only
provide very clear ways of, of supporting
the ecosystem, but also generate
initial activity and trading volumes.
And, you know, at certain key Dexis
that also within lenders as well,
so that people who don't have access
to certain types of lending can
get access, which is our charter.
Hi, I'm David Siemer a founder and CEO of
wave financial wave is an sec registered
wealth and asset management platform.
We are the managers of CX.
The early stage ecosystem fund
designed to support a, to focus
companies at the earliest stage.
Now we're very excited to launch this new
vehicle called the wave 80 yield fund.
The purpose of this fund to support
a lot of those same companies,
plus other ones that are building
decentralized finance applications.
So obviously when those companies need
support, the most is at the earliest stage
when they're first launching and that's.
We, our goal is to fill up
the TBL of those platforms.
Make sure there's a good user experience.
The trade pairs are robust.
There's always something to trade against.
So it just w w kind of a continuation
of our support from this from
C fund at the earliest stage.
So this fund has already
a nine figure vehicle.
It's going to continue to
grow pretty rapidly, and we're
really excited to be, to manage.
Hi everybody.
RD support to stay IOG way.
Stop stare.
If I know
Thank you.
Singularity net is merging artificial
intelligence with blockchain
technology through their AGI X token.
Eric sat down with CEO, Ben Gursel to
talk about bringing the token to Cardona
with their AGI X to ADA ERC 20 token
converter launching on April the 18th.
Now you can catch the conversation
in full on YouTube, right after
this, but meanwhile, here's a clip.
So today we're joined by Ben Gursel
the CEO of singularity net, and
one of the world's leading thinkers
and artificial intelligence.
So welcome to the show, Ben, and
maybe you can start off by telling
us a little bit about what the
intersection between blockchain
technology and artificial intelligence
actually is blockchain and AI.
Foundational technologies for, for
that the next few decades, they're
both key parts of, of creating a
beneficial technological singularity,
which is really, really what I'm
after with, with all of my science
and engineering and other work.
And I do think AI in a way.
The foundational technology.
I mean, if you can make a machine
smarter than people and benevolently
oriented toward people, then as I J
good said in 1965, like the first truly
intelligent machine will be the last
invention that humanity needs to make.
Right.
So in a way, AI potentially trumps
everything on, on the other hand.
How do you get to that AI that,
that trumps everything right?
And, and one key aspect, when one
thinks about the, the advent of AI
in the next years and decades is
who owns the AI, who controls the AI
based on what set of inputs is the AI
learning and evolving and developing.
And this is really where blockchain
comes in because using blockchain as
a foundation for AI, Allows AI to be
controlled in a decentralized manner
without any single point of failure,
without any single point of control.
So where does the AGI token come into
all of this for singularity net for
the blockchain aspect of, of course
we launched singularity net running
on Ethereum pretty much because.
It was there.
It was easier to work with Ethereum
smart contracts and to build their
own blockchain or to build on top
of, of Bitcoin, which didn't have as
mature of a smart contract framework.
I was never incredibly happy with.
If they're even, I mean, I love the
Ethereum guys and the philosophy of a
world's computer is, is kick-ass right.
But that celebrity is not a very
advanced programming language.
If you look at the modern theory of,
of programming languages and computer
science and proof of proof of work
in, in the form that you have in
Bitcoin or Ethereum didn't ever turn
me on too much, just because of the.
Hastening the heat death of the
universe unnecessarily and, and the
heat death of the planet as well.
Right.
So when, when I saw Cardona emerging,
based on Haskell as a smart contract
language, which is, which is.
Fundamentally superior programming
approach, just slightly what
web assembly and so forth.
And, and without this legacy of proof
of work to overcome either, it was
very appealing to move, to move the
underlayer of singular unit until.
Cardona.
Let's talk about the the process for
migrating from Ethereum to Cardona.
What does that look like for you guys?
We're looking at putting the bulk of
our effort in singularity net on the
Cardinal version version of the platform,
rather than the legacy Ethereum version.
So there's done a series of steps
after that April 18th converted launch.
So, I mean the, the next one
will probably be staking of
AIX, ADA tokens, just because.
A fairly straightforward thing to do.
And we, the staking rewards, well, we
haven't worked out all the details,
but what will probably be more
appealing than on the Ethereum version.
So we'll be, we'll be pulling pulling more
of a community who likes taking into the,
into the, the ADA native asset community.
Then the bigger step after that,
we'll be putting the whole single.
Marketplace onto, onto Cardona.
And that's, that's more of a technical
step cause we have some fairly
sophisticated sort of multi-party
escrow wallet system and so on.
And the, in the platform, we need to get
that all running in, in PLU, this then
that following step after that, which
is even further in the future, I've been
putting a bunch of time in the last few.
Into designing a new cargo side
chain customized for AI, which
is called, called hyper cycle.
Well, thank you so much for joining
us, really looking forward to
literally all the things that
you're coming out with soon.
And remember, if you want to check out
that interview in full with Ben, the link
is below and you can also find out more
about singularity nets, latest music.
So it all started with a small
but passionate community.
And since 2017, we've grown into a
fully fledged ecosystem of millions over
the past few months, that growth has
turned into something quite remarkable.
Now we recently hit something of a
milestone with 4 million tokens surpassed
and a couple of weeks ago, our research
identified around 500 projects building
on Cardone, but we have a confession to.
We got it wrong because last week
we did some further social sleuthing
and a bit of deeper digging.
And in fact, we revealed a whole new
bunch of projects building on Cardona.
We're now tracking nearly 900
projects from Dexis and defy to
of course our incredible CNF.
It's incredible growth and really
we're only just getting started,
but for newcomers, getting up
to speed can be pretty daunting.
There's some great sites out there
like Cardona queue building on CUDA,
Arno built on called Dano, ADA pulse
and many more, but we wanted to do our
bit and add to the options with the
newest central padano site and natural
evolution of the existing crowdsource
repo, where developers and creators
building on Cod Dano can log their
project from simple repo to rich directory
with Cardone technical essential.
And network updates.
Here's Morgan Schofield, our new head
of ecosystem growth to walk us through
how this community centric site now in
closed beta will enable seasoned cut on
a pros and newcomers alike, like to learn
more and to educate others on the ins
and outs of our incredibly existence.
Let's find out more.
Hi, it's great to be part of the 360
show and the team behind a central.
Central got Arnaud is a community
driven living directory of resources,
built to showcase the incredible
ecosystem building on Caetano.
We built this to be the source of truth
for you, the community to rally around and
to get access to the resources that allow
you to be the champions for the network
and the future of the Catano platform.
It's important to note that
this is not a competitor.
We really want this to be
built, to feature and showcase.
Projects that you're already working on.
If you are a community member, building
projects on the crown and network, use
this as an opportunity to showcase your
projects, to elevate and illustrate
what your team are working on.
The ask is really simple.
We would love the community to come
together and contribute to make this their
living directory of vibrant resources.
It can be think of this like a Wiki page
for Caetano and most likely Wiki page.
It takes the people and the
community around it to build
it into the valuable resource.
It can be the types of formats and content
that you can upload our videos, podcast,
audio articles developer resources,
really the sky's the limit here.
We built this to be an
open source directory.
So every time you do upload
something, There's an opportunity
for you to collaborate comment
upvote and to peer review.
What others in the
community are talking about.
This we'll start in beta mode.
We'll be releasing the website in April
for an open beta for the community to
come and contribute to the URL you should
look out for is the central caetano.io
contributions will be visible on Twitter.
And the hashtag that you should
look out for is a central
Catano or building on card.
Now let's turn to a quick
demo of the Caetano platform.
This is what a central Cardona
will start looking like.
This is the homepage landing page.
You'll be able to find any answers
you're looking for about the Caetano
project or the community around
it, much like a Reddit or a Wiki.
The most important thing is the community
adding and contributing to the resource
to contribute to your central kudos.
Super easy.
You just click on this big call
to action and it's as simple
as two clicks you can fill out.
The details of what you want to upload
once you've submitted it, that will
go to the community for review peer
review and will be eventually published
on at the central Cardone platform.
Thanks.
It's been really great being part of the
show and feel free to add me on Twitter.
My handle is empty Scofield, or just
search my name, Morgan Scofield.
So keep an eye out for central
Cardona coming out of beta very soon.
Meanwhile, you can subscribe to the
new essential Cardona newsletter
for ecosystem updates, news, and
features right to your inbox.
The link is below.
Building a global financial
operating system means scaling
from millions to billions of users.
Hydro will play an important part of
that journey with the first iteration
of the protocol already on Testnet
and being rolled out this year.
Let's hear the latest on progress
from hydro engineer, Sebastian Noggle
Sebastian.
Welcome back to cut on a 360.
Now you and the team have recently
reached quite an important model.
That's correct.
One or two weeks ago, we opened the first
hydro hats on the public Kadana Testnet.
So far we have been using local
development networks for, for
testing and really tinkering with
our hydro nodes implementation.
But this time we were like targeting
the public Kadana Testnet, which
is very important to test out the
behavior on the network, which is
very similar to the main net as it
has the same pair of meters latency.
And.
So Sebastian version zero four
is is an important new version.
Isn't it?
Yeah, just recently we cut the release
zero four, which is the first version,
which can talk to corral Testnet as it
was the one we used for our hackathon.
When we actually connected the first time
to look at our Testnet, it is working.
It is already usable, but
it's tricky to use, right?
So there is lots of things
you would need to know.
Try out.
It's a test enough.
And so there is still some things
you need to know, or for example,
some, sometimes you cannot close
the head or something like that.
So this is the first version which
can talk to the cadaver tests,
but it will not be the last one.
Right?
So we are already planning and working
on the next version, zero five, which
we'll have noticeable improvements
on, for example, handling rollbacks,
which are not done right now.
Of course, we need to do that.
One of the main things we're working
on right now and overall the next
version, zero five, we'll make it
a bit easier to use more robust to
use even on the test net and yeah.
Increase the maturity and the robustness
of the whole system as we go along.
So is there anything that the
community can do right now?
Release zero four came
with a new documentation.
We even have a new website,
which is a couple of.
And so head over to HydroDrop family,
a domain name, it couldn't pass.
And so we just use it for hosting
documentation for our work, for the work
on the hydro head protocol, noticeably
instructions, how to try it out, how to do
the demo, set up and use the hydro node.
And it will also contain as
we go along more in details
on the core concepts behind.
It will contain information about
deployment models and example use cases,
maybe how to use hydro hats and of course,
technical details like the API reference
can also be found there and going forward.
What's the next steps.
Of course, we keep on working on
implementing the hydro head protocol.
There's more leases to come as we should
see, not by now that we try to aim on
a frequent and regular release cadence.
People are expecting a main
net release of hydro insurance.
This might happen, but I want to
say something about it really,
that there is no Dooley's of hydro.
We had a couple of versions before,
and we'll have a couple of versions as
we go along becoming mature enough to
handle transactions on the main net.
So hydro deploying hydro is not
really like flipping a switch and
everything will be fast and cheap.
It's more that we build a foundation,
a piece of technology that the
builders of  can actually use and
to use, to create fast and cheap.
So as we enable our users, which is
the developers of  and developers on
Kadana use Hydra and use hydro head,
you will see some use cases become
a bit quicker, but cheaper to use.
And this is how we basically will roll
up hydro over the next couple of months.
Not another thing I would like to address
is quickly that there is no need for
a half work for hydro to be existing.
So also means that hydro
is not part of the next.
It will be benefit greatly from
the improvements, what we'll
get from the June Hartford and
maybe potentially improvements
we get from the October Hartford.
So hydro hats, people become more capable
by doing, by having these benefits,
but it's not strictly tied to it.
We will see releases of Hydra, the Hydra
note before, between, and after these.
So indeed, that's an
important point to Sebastian.
Now, if any folks watching this
want to get more involved in the
hydro journey, what can they do?
Okay.
Always, I would like to encourage
the community and especially
developers of our criminal community
to try what we've taught head
over to the hybrid.family website.
You will see communication
channels in the bottom.
We would like to hear from your
experience, from your successes,
from your failures, even, and improve
on how, what we can do and how.
Basically at the things you need
learn from your requirements
and yeah, help basically scaling
Kadana make it more capable and
ideally more adopted in the future.
Tara Virtua has been one of the pioneers
in digital art, collectibles and virtual
worlds in recent years and coming next
to Cardona NFTs and the metaverse Erik
caught up with Tara virtuous CEO, Joanne
dash RAF to find out what's happening.
NFTs and the metaverse are
critical areas for  to expand into.
And we are fortunate that we have
quite a few community projects that
are working in this area today.
We're joined by CEO of
Terra Virtua, Jawad.
Osheroff to talk a little bit about
Terra Virtua and how they're building the
metaverse with NFTs on Cardinal Jawad.
Welcome to the show.
And maybe you can start off by telling us
a little bit about the mission of terror.
Hi, I'm Eric.
Basically the mission of Tara
virtual right now is coming back
to where we started back in 2017.
We set up a metaverse in VR with
NFTs and realized back in 2018, no
one understood what any of those.
So essentially we doubled down on
NFTs and focused on being like a
premier NFT platform, respecting
IPS and working with AAA brands.
Ultimately our vision and our mission
was to create a whole metaverse
ecosystem and NFTs the digital
assets, underpin all of those.
So why decide to build Terra Virtua?
The the metaverse the whole ecosystem.
Why decide to work with Cardinal on this?
You look at the technology.
You, you look at the vision
of the people involved and you
look at the community as well.
So all three factors play together.
So when we started, we focused very much
in Ethereum, but then we were looking at
having like a really solid EVM partner.
Generally the team, the community, every
aspect of car dollar, the screens was
that this is a great place to build.
And so we basically collaborated
at the last conference.
And since then, we've been working
hand in hand with, with Cardona and
actually building out new technology
layers that will actually help the
whole LFT ecosystem become much, much
more mass, consumer friendly, you know,
ultimately the team I'll just read it.
Engaged in seeing and visionary and
metaverse is also a part of something that
called I was looking at quite heavily and
has been part of the vision from day one.
You know, here there's a vision
with NFTs and the Mexicans.
So for us, it's a good fit.
Speaking of the last summit we
collaborated on something that
involved the digital world that
was created for this summit and
Terra virtual was involved in this.
So can you tell us about
that project and where did.
So basically we provide a series of NFTs.
They were designed by Cardo themselves.
Now, what was really interesting
about this whole thing was because as
we were moving our platform towards
car data, we weren't there yet.
So we were already at an FTE's, which
are based on lithium that's one polygon.
We went there, we participated
in the conference and then we did
the first stage was just allocate
the assets to people with wallets.
So that actually had them as digital
assets, but they weren't true.
What we were actually then going
to do was mince them as NFTs
and allow them to be usable and
viewable in our 3d environments.
We have metaverse environments
we've already built and also have
the available, you know, in the
galleries, et cetera, et cetera.
And we're what we've been doing
right now for the last few months
is actually making it so that.
They can be minted they're already
in people's inventories where they
can't be mean to this true NFTs.
And then they can be moved in and out
of Terra virtual and everything else.
But there was a whole bunch of things
along the way that we discovered to make
our platform compatible with Cardona.
But like we're at the point now where
we should be able to within a few weeks
have those assets minted out to users.
And when we came up with one
approach and then we, after talking
to the team, we've actually.
Making it so that people can
actually self mint their assets.
So with that being said what, what else
can we expect in the future from Terra
Virtua, basically to date Tara virtual.
When we launched a year and a half
ago, we launched a mobile application
that did automated reality,
which allowed you to view NFTs.
We had an NFT marketplace and then
also we had our metaverse environments.
And that's the interesting thing about us.
If you look at the assets that we've
made, historically, we've collaborated
with studios, you've got Mecca Godzilla,
which is like over a million polygons.
You've got lost in space.
You've got godfather.
We created this really lovely,
3d, fully rigged assets.
And that's where we're very,
very different because.
We were going to move towards
the metaverse and in fact,
what we have online now.
So there's a massive Terrordome
where you can walk around Godzilla
and see Khan beating his chest, et
cetera, and a smaller, more intimate
space where you can put your artwork.
These will take him out of a
much, much wider environment.
So right now we're going back to.
Imminently within a few months, you're
going to see like whole metaverse spaces,
which are fully customizable with you're
able to theme everything, bringing
it these from the outside, be able to
scale assets and items and have them
run an Uber high fidelity and web GL,
because this was one of the learnings
we had, you know, we, we had a desktop
environment, but like when you do that,
when people want convenience, You lose
out on, on users and you lose out other
community and you're providing utility.
You are.
So we've been building two environments
simultaneously, which will live side
by side, and that then follows on
with the terabytes of space station.
And then after that, we can
go multiple worlds that can be
released at the end of the year.
We are actually building
a universe with multiple.
So, yeah.
Okay.
So so not only people being able to meet
their own things, but creating a space
station and a world and and multiple
other universes, lots going on with Terra
Virtua, how do they keep up with you?
How do people to stay involved?
A new mobile application is going
to be released within two weeks.
We have our Twitters and our
discords and everything else, but.
This is where we can see embracing
the community, providing a lot of
really interesting things to them,
including real-time drops real-time
comms, and also allowing people to do
very interesting things with assets.
You know, more than this here is let's
look at it and hope to speculate.
The future of NFTs is utility.
You know, doing things with
the stuff you have, right.
A good example right now is
one of our partnerships with
a company called Lightro.
And you'll be able to use that NFT
cause then you can get onto a virtual,
which I expect to have a Cardona range,
which are for chordoma community and
allow them to race the cars heads ahead.
And if I lose against you, you get
to keep our coats and sell the parts.
I'm really looking forward to seeing this.
I'm sure a lot of our viewers are so
make sure to check out Tara virtual.
All of their information is going
to be in the metadata below July.
Thanks so much for joining
us and carved out on 360.
So keep an eye out for more
from Tara virtuous soon.
And as I cryptically promised at the
start of the show today, there'll
be more NFT fund to follow at the
end of today's 360 with a special
greeting from someone you might know.
So stay tuned for that.
Meanwhile, the core development
team behind the scenes continues
to build car Dano itself.
Now here's John Kevin and Nigel to
update us, including what's to be
expected from June's vessel, heart Falk.
So John Kevin Nigel.
Welcome again.
We're going to talk about the vessel
hard-fought today, but before we do
Nigel, can you give us a little bit
of an overview of the major release
schedule and the philosophy behind that?
Sure.
Tim, as you may recall, we've opted
to concentrate efforts around three
significant releases per year, and
that's in February, June and October.
This enables our product teams to
focus on our core improvements while
we give the community plenty of lead
time necessary to prepare for any
significant changes and, or a hard fork.
And as our community grows, this
becomes more and more important
because that company that's out.
We'll want to take advantage of
the improvements we're building and
they'll need lead sign to be able to
integrate that into their development
cycles while we'll still release
smaller improvements throughout the
year, developers should look to these
three milestones as the benchmarks.
What we've outlined in our ways
to scale could Arno this year in
February, we didn't need a hard fork.
Those are normally needed
when we've got ledger changes.
However, these updates do take
us on the road towards the
basil hard-fought coming into.
And just to recap, here's
what we did in February.
We delivered the CD DL compatible
translation straight out of the CLI.
We did the infrastructure changes
necessary for incremental multisignature
where you put in a leadership schedule,
a mentor, transaction monitoring,
and also our script cost estimates.
But today what we're going to talk
about as the key Vasyl components
and that's our police version to
our script, collateral handling and
enhancements to our crypto premesis.
Thanks, Nigel.
And indeed, let's dive straight into
Plutus and Kevin now, Kevin Plutus of
course is a maturing smart contract
language, still a lots of enhancements
and improvements to go June of course,
is going to bring some significant.
Yeah, absolutely 10.
So the, these are just the first of
many improvements that we're going to
be rolling out Plutus and for vassal
in June, they're going to be four
key areas that we're focusing on.
The first one will be referenced scripts.
What these are, are on chain prerecorded.
Scripts that we can then refer
to from other transactions.
And what that means is that we will
be able to reduce the size of the
transactions that use the scripts.
And as I said, we'll
also be able to get to.
Of existing code.
So a great improvement
for adaptive elephants.
The second thing that we're rolling out
is reference inputs with reference inputs.
What you can do is you can refer
to an input in, from within a
script without consuming it.
And what that does is to allow many
scripts to refer to the same input at the
same time that improves our concurrency.
You can do many things
simultaneously using the.
Inputs a great improvement
to throughput from that.
The third thing are inline Daytons.
And what inline Dayton's do
is they make it easier for
developers to refer to a simple.
So we don't have to use hashes for inputs.
For example, we can just
refer to them directly.
It makes it easier for users
and developers to see the input.
So three great improvements.
These are covered by various CIPS that
we've put forward to the community that
have been commented on by various experts.
Our CIP 33 reference screens.
CRP 31 reference input
CIP 32 inline Daytons.
And the final thing that we're going
to be rolling out our redeemers
in transaction information and
what this starts is to let strips
cooperate by using a shared Redeemer.
So for great improvements there now,
John Crips, I primitives, we're not
talking about some of the people we
meet on crypto Twitter every day.
Yeah, not this time,
Tim, not, not this time.
We use a lot of really
cool crypto in car dyno.
In fact, state of the art, and maybe
another time I could talk about the
elliptic curve primitives we use
because we use this primitive called
82 5 5 1 9 and it's state of the
art in terms of digital signatures.
Super cool.
Today, I want to just focus on, on a
change we've made around the VRF now, VRF.
Cryptographic primitive.
And when I say primitive, it's
like little Lego bricks, little
building blocks that we, that we
build more complicated systems from.
So the VRF stands for a
verifiable, random function.
And normally when you're signing
something, you pass in the message
you're signing in the secret key,
and then you go through an algorithm
and you get a signature out.
Okay.
That signature can be verified by people.
And that's that's I think fairly
well understood by most folks.
The VRF is a little bit different.
You put in a, a secret key.
Okay.
So you need a secret, you still
need a private key, but you also
put in a kind of a random seat.
A piece of random data and during the
algorithm, rather than get a signature
out, you actually get a, what we call
a proof and another random output.
And this random output is
actually indistinguishable
from complete random noise.
And anyway, you start to give
it any kind of an insight.
Into how the VRF works.
And it's basically something
that takes the seed under secret.
And producers are proof on an
output, but we use this for our
deterministic leadership schedule.
So it's a very important aspect of
how we decide who's going to mint a
block next, anyway, it's expensive.
So with all these kinds of cryptography,
Then the math tends to be quite heavy.
They're expensive for computers
to basically calculate.
So we were using this twice and now
we've reduced that we've now managed
to kind of during the block propagation
process, rather than having two VRF
runs to two calculations, we not only.
So by doing this, we're
removing redundancy.
We're again, doing less work during our
validation and propagation of the block.
And this is all good news.
Now thing is whenever you remove something
like that's so technical like this,
you've got to be very careful how you,
how you surgically slice it out and
make sure that we truly don't need it.
But we've done this in a way where
we're faster, quicker, better, but
at the same time, just as secure,
just as deterministic as we were.
Thank you, John script, collateral
adjustment is the next thing
that we're going to cover.
Kevin, perhaps you can take that one.
We're executing a Plutus smart contract.
What we do is we have
a two phase validation.
And in the first phase, a
script is executed our offline.
We check that it's going to succeed and
only if it goes through the first place,
the validation do we then put it forward
for execution actually on the chain.
So that's the second phase of validation.
Now, what we don't want is
to have a scripts, excuse me.
That haven't been paid for.
So we require users to put up collateral
to cover the cost of executing the script.
And if the second phase failed,
then the collateral is low.
So this means that if you deliberately
submit a transaction on the chain
that you know is going to fail,
you've always had the chance to
check that through the first phase.
Then you're going to pay the collateral
cost for executing the script.
And that way you can't attack the
chain by submitting a huge number of
failing scripts, not having to pay for.
So with the current collateral
mechanism, what happens is you
put up an input and ADA input, and
if you, the transaction fails to
execute, then all of the collateral
is lost and there's a minimum value
associated with that, which is great.
Then the cost of actually
executing the script.
There's really no incentive
to try to attack the chain.
This way, what we've done is to make a
few improvements that will help a DRP user
realize that this process marks it's quite
effective is perhaps a bit draconian.
Doesn't quite meet all of the user needs
that we're seeing from adapt developers.
So what we're going to do, first of
all, is we're going to just collect.
So that it's the exact required amount.
And then the energy is never risks,
more collateral than they need to.
So you can put up 1,000,008.
I know you're a, you're
a whale, Tim, perhaps.
So you put up your million Asia and
in the old system, if you deliberately
submitted a transaction that failed,
you would have lost your million ADA.
That's a bit tough.
Now, if you do it, you'll be losing.
Much less say that'll be some percentage
of the actual script execution cost.
So a few ADA instead.
So that should make you much happier.
You won't be risking your, your
pot as collateral all the time, the
rest goes into a new change dress.
So you can specify where
the change goes to.
And of course, Kevin, that's a,
that's not the only improvement.
No, absolutely not.
So several improvements coming
from this same draft CIP the first
of which is that you're no longer
going to be restricted to ADA.
Only tokens will allow you to
use non-native tokens, aware
of a lot of DAP developers.
They.
ADA and Nonata within the same UTX house.
This can make it much easier, much simpler
for that developers to use this mechanism.
And the second improvement is that
this process is going to work much
better with hardware, wallets,
hardware, wallets will need.
That the transaction will, will succeed.
There'll be ways to check that and that
will give users scriptures as much more
confidence and certainty in the use
of polluters strips with collateral.
Cool.
Thank you, Kevin.
And of course, if you want to check
out the sip process and some of those
steps that are in flight at the moment,
we'll put a link in the notes below.
So John aside, these Plutus improvements,
there's obviously going to be some
continuing work on the network.
Perhaps you want to tell us more.
Absolutely Tim.
So, yeah.
We're going to be making
large changes this summer.
When we roll out a pipelining, I
know there was a blog that was out
there by one of our distinguished
researchers, Mathias, Fitzy.
I wanted to give people a little
bit of insight because I think
that blog was quite technical.
And when people read it, maybe it's not
clear exactly what we're delivering.
So I want to, I want to try to clear up
any misconceptions out there around this.
So whenever we're rolling.
Stuff like this, it starts, you
know, the seed starts with research.
They spend all day thinking
about this kind of stuff and, and
coming up with different models.
And it's all very academic.
At that point it's not very, it's, there's
no code, it's more thought and process.
And then we kind of, as, as these
things take shape, these enhancements,
they make, whether it's pipelining or
otherwise, as it takes shape, it becomes
more concrete, more real, more tangible.
And we think, okay, yeah, this is
something we can actually make a change
to, and it will have real impact for the.
That process then goes to, to folks
like me in the architecture section.
And I will take the research input.
That's my job to take that and turn
it into a more tangible specification.
We call it an engineering
spec or architectural spec.
And then indeed it goes to the guys who do
the actual work, the engineers and they,
they take my work and then they write the
code and that's how, that's how we do it.
And I think folks who maybe
read Matthias's blog he speaking
from a very academic standpoint.
So there, when we, what we've
been calling pipelining on the.
It's really about getting the blocks
transmitted faster to your neighbor.
And I've discussed that before,
because the faster the blocks can
transmit, the more kind of headroom we
have to increase network parameters,
make things faster, bigger, better.
When Mathias is thinking about
this, he's not thinking about,
about the, the downstream impact.
He's very focused on, on, on
all of the different variants of
pipeline and that you can have.
So you might've heard words
like pipelining, diffusion,
pipelining, a synchronous
validation, delayed validation.
They're all different flavors of the
same idea, which is to bring together
the process of validating a block
whilst you're also communicating and
transmitting the data as fast as possible.
Now, when we're selecting, which one
of the brilliant ideas, our research
geniuses come up with, we have to do
so with a pragmatic hat on, because
we have to say to ourselves, This this
version, they synchronous validation.
Maybe it's a little bit faster, but it's
more dangerous and it needs more time.
So we've chosen what we're
calling diffusion pipelining.
Okay.
And that's why I call it a pipelining
on the show, which we feel as a suite.
Which will deliver plenty of
headroom for amazing changes to
come for the rest of the year.
So we may go back and look at
other things like asynchronous
validation and other things that
lead to to even higher throughput.
But you gotta remember we are
already ahead in terms of our, our
performance roadmap as is where we were.
Our block utilization is still
not at a hundred percent.
We have a big changes coming in June.
That's going to let us really
ramp up the network parameters
and increase block size and speed.
And yeah.
Then on top of that, just compounding.
We may never end up doing a different
variant of pipelining because
actually I believe what we're going
to bring in June is going to be
the sweet spot and we'll be enough.
And then we're going to be moving
to input endorsers, which is a
radically different way of doing
consensus and doing block propagation.
And we can talk about that in detail.
Another time effectively, you have
ranking blocks and input blocks, and
it's, it's all quite sophisticated, but
I think pipelining and the way we're
bringing it in June is going to be.
Headroom until input endorsers
comes, which is effectively an
end game solution that will see us
scale out for the next five years.
Thank you, John, for that overview Nigel.
So work continues a pace on preparing
for the June facile hard-fought, but
of course, October is coming down
the line and it'll arrive sooner
than we think that's going to be
called the Chang hard fork as well.
A few bits and pieces
being worked on right now.
What's the update.
Of course, Tim, our team is starting
to plan for the Chang hard fork in
October and while the full scope is
still in development which will change
over the coming weeks and months.
We definitely know certain things
that are going to be in the pipeline
for October and our community
can look forward to seeing.
And more about these in the near future.
We've got changes in
the area of governance.
We've got more smart contracts,
evolution, we've got more changes
and improvements to performance.
And of course that's just
the core development.
As we've shared previously, we've got also
lots of other exciting things coming in
the pipeline from light wallets to site.
Thank you Nigel.
So I hope as you can see a huge amount
of work going on for June, and we're
also thinking ahead to October already,
gentlemen, thank you very much for
joining us and we'll see you again.
See another great update
from the team there.
Now let's check out some of the projects
building on Codonics wing writers,
JPEG store are gone and Typhon wallet.
This week.
I got a chance to speak with
some of the teams building on.
We spoke with JPEG store Typhon wallet.
I had gone interviewing writers.
So tell us what is your mission
and how is it different from other
pre-existing solutions on the market?
My name's Liam.
I'm from a project called wing writers.
We're building a decentralized
exchange on Caetano.
We're powered by vacuum labs,
which means we come from one of the
longest working development shops
in the space overall longer term.
Our mission is really to be a layer
of the infrastructure and Caetano,
you know, dApps and other platforms
or projects that are building on
Caetano are going to require someone
who can do swaps for them very
securely and safely, and can integrate
really deeply into their platforms.
So that's who we want to be.
So we're in June.
We're the largest NFT
marketplace on car dauno.
And our mission is really to grow
car Dano and bring as much users
as we can into our ecosystem.
We're a fun, vibrant, funky, and Ft
marketplace, and we're bringing lots of
exciting new features to our platform.
Such as offers auctions trading profiles.
We also have a launchpad for creators.
We're really trying to bring more creators
into the space and make it as easy as
possible for them to create on Cardinal.
When we launched, we were also, I
think the first NFT marketplace on
Kronos fully integrated with royalties.
So working.
Creators and supporting them has
really been a big mission for us.
Since the beginning I got mission
is to create a decentralized cloud
computing marketplace enabling us to
contribute, to and make use of secure,
private self sovereign cloud platform.
Our fall shower sharding.
And sharding mechanism, distribution model
based on the learning, the behavior of
our resource providers enables us to store
files in nos that fit their requirements.
This goes in, hand-in-hand
such as for GDPR compliance.
If you want to be a green
eco-friendly project green
energy use and high-performance
et cetera we had type one.
All it are positioning ourselves.
From a ground zero approach
of, of development.
The core libraries that
are used by wallets for
generating  signing transactions.
I've built from ground zero in
pure JavaScript by our developers.
And we are addressing the
gap in the ecosystem by.
Giving features to the users which
are not available in some of the
wallets or were not available earlier
when we launched diamond wallet
things like attaching metadata to
a transaction and allowing users to
send multiple tokens in a transaction.
What are the advantages
of building on Cordato?
Why are you in Cardona
as opposed to any other.
There's really two pieces.
The first piece is the functional approach
in programming languages on Caetano.
Brian is very much makes a difference.
And the second piece is the whole sort
of philosophy behind Cardona to move a
little bit slower and maybe consider.
Problems from a little bit, a
little bit more of a strategic
level, make sense, right?
If you look over the last 12
months, there's more and more
people building on Cardona.
And I think largely it's driven by those,
those two reasons, the functional aspect
and the kind of, long-term more considered
approach to development of the space.
One of the best things about the
Cardona ecosystem is the community.
From the beginning, we.
So much support and love from
the people inside Cardona.
And I think anyone who's trying
to build something unique and
interesting for our ecosystem is
going to get the same type of support.
The reason why we chose to build
on Cardona in the first place is
just because of the vision and
the mission behind the blockchain.
We really, really resonated with
Cardona's a fully decentralized.
Like the people's blockchain.
We love what they're doing in Africa.
Cardona is really focused
on real-world applications.
I think it can bring a lot
more people on board with the
technology and into the ecosystem.
In general, we see.
Being a blockchain that's
truly going to take crypto.
It's a mass market.
Yeah.
We can talk for a down a lot.
I mean there could go on a long time,
but I'll just list a few points there
that, that stand out the most it security
decentralization, which kind of go hand
in hand research-driven approach you
know, building up, studying the models
before they actually implement the
code capital efficiency ecosystem and
future potential, which is in Africa.
People that don't have
that capacity, right?
We are in Chicano from 2017 and I'm,
I'm a, I'm a computer science graduate.
So I love technology and
Cardenas technology is what
brought me into the ecosystem.
So We actually built CareNow
scan the Explorer earlier.
And then we started
building type and wallets.
So our low bit Carano is, is
the technology, the technical
foundation of Caetano.
And then when the catalyst
launched it provided us a great
platform to find our work.
And then we went fully independent
and now we are working fully
independent into Cardona ecosystem,
and we are really happy with.
So how's it going?
What stage are you at now?
So w we've put out our test
nets, we're moving to main net
in about a week to seven days.
We've gone through a security audit
by cirrhotic, which was finished
and we put a blog post out about it.
About a week ago.
We're doing just our final
security testing with our own.
I'm on squished through that.
We'll move to my net and then we'll
sort of make more announcements.
But yeah, our plan is to
get this done pretty quick.
We're integrated with a bunch of
different wallets, Flint, 60 volt
NAMI and then a new fire as well.
So we're fully launched, like we said
earlier, we are the largest empty
marketplace on Cardona and we've
held that position for three months.
But we're now at a stage where we're
profitable and we're hiring grafts.
So we're looking for engineers, community
managers, marketers, the best talent we
can get inside of the ecosystem to really.
Take our marketplace to the
next level and start competing
with the other blockchains.
I think we've basically refactored
the entire code base and migrated
our database, which just went
live a couple of days ago.
So now we're gonna switch and
focus on really pushing out
new features a lot faster.
There's a lot of core functionality.
We still want to get down like
auctions and offers, but there's
also a lot of just new things we
want to bring to the ecosystem and.
Like find new ways to create features
that will be interesting for you.
Is it we're focusing first on
setting up the marketplace the award
scheme and a required infrastructure
around the shared storage economy.
At, at the time, at the moment
we're working on porting MVP we
presented to some of our partners.
In CodeNow and also in the traditional
space and we'll continue our testing on
the UI UX we're planning audits, following
the community testing and a thorough
testing phase prior to public launch.
We just want to we just recently
released information on our ERC 20.
Which integrates nomad, I'm a committer
and a very easy to use front end,
allowing users and projects to migrate
from ERC 20 to Coronado native tokens.
Tycon wallet is at a development
stage, which is a staple.
We are enhancing the features that,
that we have already developed.
We are improving the UI, the
user interface we have recently
redesigned the full wallet from.
Like pulling from scratch.
It's a new interface.
We introduced doc mode and now we
are venturing into other platforms
like mobile and tech stop.
So to launch and to find staying
power are two different things.
Post-launch what are a few
crucial milestones on the
path to you guys becoming a
permanent part of this ecosystem?
Crypto as a general rule, tends
to lean on that first part.
Extracting as much attention as possible
in the beginning, and then trying to
execute later we're very different.
We're developer led, you know, by being
associated with vacuum labs who are
very strong on the development side,
we're really trying to build a product
before we sort of progressed to any level
where we're trying to shill out product.
Like everyone's going to be
able to get on the test now.
Right.
That's very much aligned with our ethos.
So we think people seeing the product,
seeing our roadmap saying at the
functionality and improvements,
we're looking at over time, you
know, our roadmaps really build out.
We're adding more wallets.
We've got more features.
We've got staking in yield
farming, both coming.
So all of these things, I think delivering
like a constant supply of new features
and functionality, listening to.
And then really addressing any
issues and shortcomings you have.
I think that tide makes
you more sustainable.
I can power again, our mission.
Now that we're number one is to
really start bringing more users to
Cardona and growing the ecosystem.
So.
We're trying to find new artists
and creators to partner up with as
well as supporting the incredible
existing ones that have already
built collections here on Cardona.
We can also grow our launchpad more.
We're looking to hire a large private
manager there, and I think there's a lot
of documentation that we can create to
help people with the minting process.
Just, yeah, get more resources out there
to make it easier for people to create.
And bring more of like, Into the
ecosystem if achieving proper
decentralization and a sufficient
node coverage to offer secure GDPR
compliance are important steps towards
delivering on potential of our solution.
In addition, key partnerships, such as
our joint venture program with genius.
And also, and our expansion as he to
our NMT repetition model are important
milestones that are in launch.
In addition to development of our public
storage social platform called after we
launched the wallet we want to continue
to build this wallet and continue
to upgrade as, and when the Cardinal
heart Cardinal upgrades, heart-focused
into new and new era, we have so many
hard folks planned for this year.
It's going to be next year.
So we are not stopping here.
We are driving to.
Lauren and lock features into the wallet.
One more thing to mention.
We also launched that
connector a while ago.
So it's a unique approach
again from the CIP.
And we are also building out more
and more features and documentation
around that connector for different.
How do you see your project niche
developing on Cordato and in the
wider industry over the longterm?
And what problems do you feel that your
project is uniquely positioned to it?
Let me start with the second part first.
I mean, I think the first part is
if you're not building I've been
in crypto about six, seven years.
If you're not really building
effectively with a good development
team, then essentially in this
industry, you're just marketing, right?
Like you're leveraging someone
else's product to package it
together with some sort of concept.
Where the other end of the spectrum,
like we have we a backbone lab,
very, very strong development team.
That's the way, you know, we didn't come
out of stealth until we're a hundred
percent sure that we could execute
and what we're trying to execute.
We tend to be probably more
risk averse than other projects.
You know, we speak pretty regularly
about how we're structuring our
product how we're approaching defy
and those types of opportunities.
We talk to our compliance team.
We talk to our legal advisors, right?
So w we're trying to obviously
build a project that's sustainable.
So all of our users can use
us for a long time to come.
We're planning to incorporate you peg
store as a B corporation, where a portion
of our company's profits will actually go
towards environmental and social causes.
And this is something we're
really passionate about.
We think we can build a company that
is truly different and focused on our
community and Cardinal and, and gives
back rather than just extracting.
And we hope that this will pave the way
for future entrepreneurs to follow in our.
We're uniquely positioned to provide a
decentralization, decentralized compute
services, resources, to projects, wanting
to build truly user solving applications
and believe we can make, make a positive
contribution to the development that's
taking place in the third world countries.
So somewhat similar to
what cradle is doing, where
possible through partnerships.
Where we can contribute to these
countries that are in need.
We also think we will solve a
bigger barrier in adoption and
migration from traditional space to
the blockchain space, by providing
an easy to use clean interface.
We are in the ecosystem from a long
time, and we were observed observing
that there's so many features that
Cardinal has that were not being taken
advantage of by the wallet providers.
The, the users You know,
big becoming so much.
It's, it's like the users when see
a wallet interface, they see, okay,
this is what Caetano does, but Carano
provides a lot more functionality.
So that's where we came in the picture
providing so many features that were
not available with existing wallets.
But Gaetano as a backend
technology does provide it.
This was one of the main features.
We, we provided a simple
interface for users.
The second transaction and
add a message along with it.
And any type of message.
Any kind of complex message, not just,
not just a, a text message, but like
a Jason, you know, like committed data
for a token, you could attach anything.
And there was another unique feature
of Cardona was ability to send, not
just one token, but more than that,
tens of hundreds of tokens, along with
the transaction, that's the main goal.
That's the goal that we started building
type and wallet with allowing users
to utilize the core Carano technology.
Thank you for joining us on the show today
and thank you to the audience for joining
us also tune in next time for more.
And of course, additional kudos to
wing rise there for their recent
support of the mince swap team.
This community is as much a part of what
makes Cardona as special as the tech.
Now remember defy is exciting, but
we're early be careful about that.
So that's nearly a wrap
for March before we go.
A shout out to the team at DC spark,
who this week launched the middle COVID
aside chain and important new step and
car darnos interoperability journey.
Hey guys, this is Nico core of
middle Camilla for the ones that
don't know that we just launched.
Thanks.
Looking pretty good.
for Carolina that allows for  to be
launched on the site, which is pretty cool
because you can use ADA for everything
that's related to these idiom tabs.
Things are looking pretty well,
and I'm very excited to eventually
I joined the show and tell you
more about what's going on.
We'll have the team on soon to
tell us how it's all been going.
Now, if you haven't already make sure
you do the like subscribe and bell
thing, lots of links below for you to
check out after including that interview
with Ben, the IHK blog for more on
car Dano and the growing X system out.
Of course, if you want to subscribe to
that newest central car Dano newsletter,
you'll find the links below there too.
So thanks for joining.
And we'll see you at the next
360 show at the end of April.
That's the 28th.
Let's play out with this.
Hey, Chimp, I've been checking
out that car down on his way at
three stuff was exciting to me.
Yeah, they got some cool claymations too.
Oh shit.
That's my music.
Hey stupid, Charles Hoskinson here.
I'm trying to get contact with you, man.
Call me sometime.
Let's hook it up.